F. Peter Libassi Papers 1998.0333
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
F. Peter Libassi Papers
undated,1963-1977
1998.0333
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
1.3 Linear feet
The collection contains publications, proposals, petitions, photographs and plans for the "new community" and documentation of the Greater Hartford Process, Inc.
Libassi, F. Peter.
Biography
F. Peter Libassi was born in New York City (1930) and received his B.A. from Colgate University (1951) and his LL.B. from Yale University (1954). He is the former President of the Children's Fund of Connecticut and former Dean of the Barney School of Business at the University of Hartford. Libassi also served as Senior Vice President of the Travelers Corporation and as General Counsel for the U.S. Department Health, Education and Welfare (HEW) and President of the Greater Hartford Process.
Early in 1969, business leaders in the Greater Hartford region organizaed the Greater Hartford Corporation. Their action was born out of the frustration of the 1960s, which had not produced coalitions broad enough or programs big enough to cope with urban blight and suburban sprawl. In their words: "The initial goal of the corporation will be the creation of a model of what Greater Hartford can be like if its people decide to make it so....The corporation will seek community adoption and implementation of the total program developed. It will undertake to bring the resources and capabilities of private industry together with the public agencies..."
One of the two new nonprofit public service corporations created as part of the process was the Greater Hartford Process, Inc.. Formed in January 1971 to examine the region, set forth the goals and the arithmatic for a better region, and design specific proposals to bring about a region the "works," the Board of Directors of the "Process" was to broaden the initial business-based effort with a coalition representing business, labor, residents, local government and planning agencies. The second nonprofit corporation was the Greater Hartford Community Development Corporation (DevCo) which was to serve as the development instructment of the "Process." According to the documents in the collection, the Greater Hartford Community Development Corporation ( DevCo) proposed the gradual creation of a "new community" over 15 years on approximately 1,500 acres of land located in the northwest corner of Coventry, Connecticut.
See The Greater Hartford Process for futher history and details on the project.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains publications, proposals, petitions, photographs and plans for the "new community" and documentation of the Greater Hartford Process, Inc.
Arrangement
Series I: New Community in Coventry ( undated, circa 1973-1974 )
Series II: Speech Materials--Resource ( undated, 1963-1977 )
Series III: Greater Hartford Process ( 1970-1977 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to various aspects of Connecticut history and Connecticut politics. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Additional materials about the Greater Hartford Process are available in the Arthur Lumsden Papers and interviews with associated individuals in the Center for Oral History Interviews Collection.
Libassi materials are also available at Yale University.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Demographic profile of the City of Hartford 1960 and 1970 Dodd
Economic Interdependence in the Greater Hartford Region -- City and Suburbs Dodd
The Greater Hartford Process Dodd
Greater Hartford: The Total Approach Dodd
Hartford: Fiscal Problems of an Aging City, Vols. I-II Dodd
The Influence of a regional economy on Hartford's Population Dodd
A new community in Coventry Dodd
The New Englaner, June 1973 Dodd
Northwest Hartford: An Action Program Dodd
Opening up the suburbs Dodd A 10127
Dodd
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Mr. Libassi in 1998.
Greater Hartford Process, Inc.; Coventry (Conn.); Notes.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Publications.
- Series I: New Community in Coventry, undated, circa 1973-1974
  - Clippings, undated, 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Environmental Impact, 1974 September (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Exhibits, 1974 September (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Municipal Impact, 1974 September (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Petition to establish the boundaries of a planned community zone and to approve the general development plan..., 1974 September (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, circa 1973 (Box 2:, Folder 6)
  - Proposed zoning regulation for a planned community, 1974 September (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Population projections, 1974 September (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Workbook: The New Community in Coventry, 1974 May (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Workbook: The New Community in Coventry (annotated), 1974 May (Box 1:, Folder 10)
- Series II: Speech Materials--Resource, undated, 1963-1977
  - undated, 1963-1973 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - 1971-1977 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - undated, 1971-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 13-14)
- Series III: Greater Hartford Process, 1970-1977
  - Budget and program reports, 1976-1977 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Hartford Process, 1970 February (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - History (Part I), 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - History (Part II), 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - History (pp. 326-Appendices), circa 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Oral History (draft), 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Program management (FY 1977/78), 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 21)